Abraham Harriton Papers
Abraham Harriton Papers
1915-1965
Harriton, Abraham, 1893-1986
1.25 linear ft.
Correspondence (1937-1965); personal papers (1950-1952); photographs of Harriton and his work (1918-1962); manuscripts by Harriton on art and artists (1949-1964); scrapbooks (1915-1962); published material (1922-1964); and biographical material.
Correspondents include Bernard Berenson, Isabel Bishop, Philip Evergood, Ralph Fabri, Hans Hofmann, Elia Kazan, Leon Kroll, Peter Neagoe, Edward G. Robinson, Raphael Soyer, Max Weber, and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
149039
Biographical History
American Jewish painter. Born in Bucharest, Rumania.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1914 to 1970, the Abraham Harriton Papers comprises correspondence, artwork and memorabilia of the Rumanian-born American Jewish painter. Documenting his professional life, the collection not only illuminates Harriton's growth and development as an artist, but also reflects his political orientation amidst the turbulence of the depression.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-Subject Files include both incoming and outgoing letters and other material relating to individuals as well as organizations. Correspondents include fellow artists (Isabel Bishop, Sidney Dickinson, Philip Evergood, Marie Zoe Greene, Hans Hofmann, Leon Kroll, Ross Moffett, Katherine Nash, Raphael Soyer, Harwood Steiger, Abraham Walkowitz, Max Weber); art critics and authors (Bernard Berenson, A.L. Chanin, Howard Devree, Edward Alden Jewell, Peter Neagoe, Harry Salpeter); and patrons (Edith Halpert, Joseph H. Hirshhorn, Alexander Z. Kruse, A. Philip McMahon, Henry I. Riker, Ralph E. Samuel). Organizational correspondence encompasses gallery affiliations (ACA Gallery, Anderson Galleries, Garelick's Gallery); museums (Art Institute of Chicago, Carnegie Institute, Metropolitan Museum of Art, National Academy of Design, Whitney Museum of American Art); and professional organizations (An American Group, Audubon Artists, National Institute of Arts and Letters, National Society of Painters in Casein, Inc., Provincetown Art Association).
Artwork includes a single original watercolor sketch and reproductions, both printed and photographic, of Harriton's paintings. In addition, two scrapbooks containing reproductions of Harriton's work, writings, clippings about the artist, and a pencil sketch may also be found among these materials. Arranged by subject, Writings encompass both Harriton's artistic philosophy and painting technique.
Photographs and printed material, including clippings (1914-1964) and exhibition catalogs, invitations and announcements (1915-1968) constitute Memorabilia.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959.; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973.; Fabri, Ralph, 1894-; Harriton, Abraham, 1893-1986.; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966.; Kazan, Elia.; Kroll, Leon, 1884-1974.; Neagoe, Peter; Robinson, Edward G., 1893-1973.; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987.; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists, Jewish -- United States.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Romanian Americans.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - ACA Galleries, 1944-1962 (Box 1)
  - American Artist, 1951; 1960 (Box 1)
  - American Artists' Congress, program (Box 1)
  - An American Group, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Anderson Galleries (New York, NY), 1922; auction catalog, receipt (Box 1)
  - Archives of American Art, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Artists for Victory, Inc., 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1938; 1943 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, Inc., 1955-1960 (Box 1)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1955-1956; undated (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Isabel, 1953-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - Bocour, Leonard, 1950; undated (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1941-1950 (Box 1)
  - Chanin, A.L., 1950 (Box 1)
  - College Art Association, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Press, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Devree, Howard, See The New York Times
  - Dickinson, Sidney, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Dodd, Lamar, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Downtown Community School (New York, NY), 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Engle, Michael M., 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Evergood, Philip, 1940-1965 (Box 1)
  - Fabri, Ralph, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Garelick's Gallery (Detroit, MI), 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Gayle, Margot, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Greene, Marie Zoe, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Halpert, Edith G., 1922 (Box 1)
  - [Joseph H.] Hirshhorn Collection, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Hofmann, Hans, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Jewell, Edward Alden, See The New York Times
  - Kazan, Elia, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Kroll, Leon, 1958; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Kruse, Alexander Z., 1946 (Box 1)
  - McMahon, A. Philip, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1941-1955 (Box 1)
  - Moffett, Ross, 1956; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Nash, Katherine, 1962 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Design, 1918; 1930 (Box 1)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1955-1963 (Box 1)
  - National Society of Painters in Casein, Inc., 1956 (Box 1)
  - Neagoe, Peter, 1945 (Box 1)
  - The New York Times, 1937-1962; n.d. (Box 1)
  - Pfeiffer, Fritz and Hope, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Piper, Raymond F, 1952-1960 (Box 1)
  - Provincetown Art Association, Inc., 1952; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Riker, Henry I., 1915 (Box 1)
  - Robinson, Edward G., 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Salpeter, Harry, 1937; n.d. (Box 1)
  - Samuel, Ralph E., 1954 (Box 1)
  - Silvermine Guild of Artists, Inc., 1963 (Box 1)
  - Soyer, Ralph, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Steiger, Harwood, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Walkowitz, Abraham, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Wares, James A., 1951 (Box 1)
  - Weber, Max, 1940-1951 (Box 1)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1936-1962 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Original
    - Watercolor sketch, untitled (Box 1)
  - Reproductions
    - Clippings (by title, A-Z) (Box 1)
    - Greeting card, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Photographs (by title, A-P), 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Photographs (by title, Q-Z and unidentified), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Slides (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 scrapbooks, with reproductions, writings, and clippings. Scrapbook 1 contains a single pencil sketch. (Box 2)
- Writings (by subject)
  - Artistic philosophy (Box 2)
  - Painting technique (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs, Harriton, ca. 1902-1962 (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1914-1960s; n.d.; clippings; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Exhibitions, invitations, announcements, 1915-1968; n.d.; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)